<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Teaching | Codematician]]></title>
  <link href="http://andy.terrel.us/blog/categories/teaching/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andy.terrel.us/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-05T14:56:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://andy.terrel.us/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andy R. Terrel]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Usefulness of a University]]></title>
    <link href="http://andy.terrel.us/blog/2013/04/08/use-of-a-university/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-08T21:08:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://andy.terrel.us/blog/2013/04/08/use-of-a-university</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/2013-swc-arizona.html">The post reiterating that the biggest problem in teaching software carpentry (SWC)]
</a> is
installation, got me all in a tissy.  I even signed up for their mailing list!</p>

<p>My first impression with SWC was a wonderful community that in encouraging
folks to learn computing skills.  After witnessing the TeachScheme movement, I
was skeptical that two day bootcamps could really have any impact, but then
again I'm usually wrong.  Now coming off two and a half years of supporting
users on supercomputers, I too see the frustration that started SWC in the
first place.  Scientists waste quite a lot of time not using the tools
effectively, but then again I waste too much time futzing with tools.  The
current frustration is over the view of what education of these tools actually
is.</p>

<h2>What is a university education?</h2>

<p>Some of my best friends in life were made in the classrooms of my
university education.  While learning the essence of science, math and
philosophy, something else was happening as well.  I was participating in a
community of learning.  These friends were the ones who helped me struggle
through problems, understand new topics, and motivate my continued education.</p>

<p>While one can go through Bloom's Taxonomy and be as theoretical as one likes, I
have yet to see many people actually discuss the building of a community around
your classroom.  For most open source developers, this is the major draw, to
work on hard problems with a set of intellectually challenging peers.  I will
say that some tools are being developed to help this, such as Piazza. At the
end of the day, MOOCs, bootcamps, and plain-ol-lectures that don't give
students the ability to actively engage an topic on their own terms isn't worth
its salt.  Developing communities around learning is another method for
continuing the education process.</p>

<p>Perhaps the only thing that a University is providing that other methods of
teaching hasn't touched is this community of learning.  To me that's the
biggest problem in alternative university education, there is no community of
learning after the day ends.</p>

<p>(On that note I have an unfunded grant proposal to turn textbooks into
community initiators. Perhaps I'll get my act together and pursue it again.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
