<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Codematician - NumPy</title><link href="http://andy.terrel.us/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/numpy-tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://andy.terrel.us/</id><updated>2013-07-18T16:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Homepage of Andy R. Terrel</subtitle><entry><title>Women in Scientific Computing, SciPy 2013</title><link href="http://andy.terrel.us/blog/2013/07/18/women-sci-comp/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-18T16:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-07-18T16:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Kristen M. Thyng</name></author><id>tag:andy.terrel.us,2013-07-18:/blog/2013/07/18/women-sci-comp/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post written by &lt;a href="http://kristenthyng.com/"&gt;Kristen M. Thyng&lt;/a&gt; about an event we both worked to organize at SciPy2013.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/1-IMG_0723.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/2-IMG_0726.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in other computing fields, women make up a small percentage of the people in scientific computing. In order to bring together the women at the SciPy conference to aid in building community …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post written by &lt;a href="http://kristenthyng.com/"&gt;Kristen M. Thyng&lt;/a&gt; about an event we both worked to organize at SciPy2013.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/1-IMG_0723.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/2-IMG_0726.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in other computing fields, women make up a small percentage of the people in scientific computing. In order to bring together the women at the SciPy conference to aid in building community and to discuss related issues, a mixer was held during one of the evening Birds of a Feather sessions, moderated by SciPy Conference co-chair Andy Terrel and attendee Kristen Thyng. The mixer was co-sponsored by generous support from NumFOCUS, the Python Software Foundation, and the SciPy conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approximately three women attended SciPy 2012. In 2013, there was a substantially higher representation of women, with about 35 women or 10% of the participants between the tutorials, the conference, and the sprints. However, this number is still low, and more elucidating is how the numbers break down by participation activity. More detailed numbers for female participation are as follows, noting that some of these numbers are exact and some are rough best estimates since demographic information was not gathered from conference participants:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/18 active program committee members&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 of about 10 lightning talks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/5 awardees for the plotting competition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 of about 20 tutorial leaders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2/13 sponsored students&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3/19 conference co-chairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authors or co-authors on at least 13 of 120 submissions &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least 3 of 27 poster presenters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least 4 of 70 speakers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/3-IMG_0728.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/4-IMG_0732.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after arriving at the event, people became acquainted with each other and started chatting. There was a good number of people at the mixer to meet new people but still have a chance to meet everyone. There were, all together, 16 people at the mixer: 13 women and 3 men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the group formed a circle in order to have a chance to have a discussion. The discussion covered many topics. Specific special interest groups for women in computing were brought up and women attending the mixer had positive things to say about the groups. In fact, many of them were attending the conference due to encouragement from PyLadies. They found that PyLadies was a less intimidating way to meet and talk and learn about Python than a regular Meetup group. In particular, some women found the Learn Python group to be helpful. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For helping to get women (and men) who are already interested in computing to learn more and therefore be able to participate more in a conference like SciPy, it was suggested to have a separate tutorials and talk track for introductory material, and have proper tools for self-assessment to make sure participants can correctly choose their path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked whether a separate women's track at the conference would be desirable, participants said that they would not like this because they would rather be able to attend whatever track best fit their interests, and would not like to be singled out when it came to the research material itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentorship at the next SciPy between women (and possibly men) who have previously attended a SciPy (or related) conference was suggested to help new participants feel more comfortable in what might be a new community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was brought up that few iPython (and other package) contributors are women. Possible reasons suggested to explain this included that women may not feel comfortable contributing when men are aggressive and blunt. This is something that could be addressed by increased understanding and awareness on all sides. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference Code of Conduct was brought up as was how prominent to make the statement and how best to preempt any potential problems. Participants agreed that having previously established rules for how to deal with problems was worth any time that was spent on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was unanimous that people at the SciPy conference had been accepting and friendly to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A question brought up was how to get more women involved with conference planning, which could then in turn help the conference be more inclusive and diverse in the future, keeping in mind that sometimes women are cautious not to be stuck "just" planning and organizing, which could be considered a traditionally female task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get more women to attend SciPy and submit abstracts, people thought that helping with the process could be beneficial. This sort of support would be most logical to come from a group like PyLadies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/5-IMG_0736.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/6-IMG_0737.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;45%"&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various organizations were suggested as being helpful to seek out, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://numfocus.org"&gt;NumFOCUS&lt;/a&gt; (has funds for scholarships and women intiatives along with resources)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://adainitiative.org"&gt;Ada Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.pyladies.com"&gt;PyLadies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/OutreachProgramForWomen"&gt;Outreach Program for Women (OPW)&lt;/a&gt; (Internships for women in computing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/GnomeWomen"&gt;GNOME Women&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.engr.utexas.edu/wep/"&gt;Women in Engineering&lt;/a&gt; (UT program to encourage and provide support for female students in the engineering program. Similar programs are sometimes available at other universities.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; (teaching/learning materials are available online)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.girlswhocode.com"&gt;Girls Who Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A general suggestion for getting more people to SciPy was to have differentiated funding for people coming from companies versus those who are paying their own way (and are not academics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, a good time was had by all and it was very enjoyable meeting and discussing with a small group of like-minded individuals. Having these sorts of discussions could be helpful in having a more diverse set of scientific coders over time! For more information about this event, contact Andy Terrel at andy.terrel [at] gmail.com or Kristen Thyng at kthyng [at] gmail.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://andy.terrel.us/figures/7-IMG_0738.JPG" title="Image title&amp;quot; width=&amp;quot;90%"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="NumPy"></category><category term="SciPy"></category></entry><entry><title>NumPy SciPy Benchmarks</title><link href="http://andy.terrel.us/blog/2013/07/07/numpy-scipy-benchmarks/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-07T21:08:00-07:00</published><updated>2013-07-07T21:08:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Andy R. Terrel</name></author><id>tag:andy.terrel.us,2013-07-07:/blog/2013/07/07/numpy-scipy-benchmarks/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At PyCon2013, a group of about 30 developers got together to discuss
NumPy and SciPy.  The room mostly included folks that use NumPy and
SciPy extensively, such as myself, a few who were just learning, and
several core contributors (if not currently in the past), such as Eric
Jones, Travis …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At PyCon2013, a group of about 30 developers got together to discuss
NumPy and SciPy.  The room mostly included folks that use NumPy and
SciPy extensively, such as myself, a few who were just learning, and
several core contributors (if not currently in the past), such as Eric
Jones, Travis Oliphant, Anthony Scopatz, and Jake Vanderplas.  It was
an impromptu meeting, as most birds of a feather sessions are, so I
don't think we even got the full number of interested participants at
PyCon2013.  The scientific large support at PyCon was surprising,
since most of us scientists think the wider Python ecosystem leaves us
behind in many of their activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were three topics we discussed: briefly about the development and
maintenance of the libraries, about the use of newer technologies, e.g. Cython,
PyPy, Copperhead, Numba, and finally about having a benchmark for new
implementations of NumPy to see how complete they are.  Since there were not
very many core developers in the room, it was hard to really push a topic on
the development side but the other two topics were the most discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To briefly summarize the maintenance and future plans section, I asked about
how the community was doing since I've been organizing this whole conference
thing and haven't been on the mailing lists in a while. Travis mentioned that
NumFOCUS was trying to raise money for the projects, especially around the
topic of paying a maintainer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Miniature Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we turn to the topic of benchmarks.  At the end we decided that there are
at least two types of benchmarks that are really needed by the community.
First, is a set of miniature applications that show off the tools well.  Since
there is such a wide variety of tools available right now, it is difficult to
know what to invest in as a developer.  Ian Osvald mentioned his book that
includes one of the only major comparisons I've seen in the tools.  I suggested
we look at how the Mantevo project implemented its mini-apps for the US DOE.
Another suggestion was to organize the applications in the seven dwarfs
of scientific computing suggested by Phil Collela. I believe these have been
renamed to motifs and extended to eleven by the Berkeley crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea moving forward will be to collect a number of applications, give a
reference implementation, and accept contributions showing how to implement
them in a Python runnable way.  The idea is not to make everyone use Python for
everything but to show off the capabilities of Python as an integration (and
implementation) platform.  One participant brought up that we could have a site
like the Computer Language Benchmarks, while we agreed in spirit enough of us
do not like that benchmark because of its purist ideas that applications should
stick to a single language.  To be friendly to vendor solutions, I'm willing to
accept closed runtimes but since the point is to highlight the code, all code
must be free and open, preferably BSD.  I am sure we will refine the rules as
we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NumPy Benchmarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matti, a contributor to NumPyPy, brought up the idea of creating a suite of
benchmarks to compare different implementations of NumPy.  The idea here is
once again not to compete ruthlessly for fame and glory, but rather provide a
baseline for developer to hit when implementing alternatives and users to know
how complete and single implementation is. Right now I know of several NumPy
implementations (or close to implementations), e.g., NumPyPy, Numba,
Copperhead, and a benchmark will be a welcome addition to the tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan to start off will be to grab out some tests from the NumPy regression
tests and grab a benchmark runner.  Matti suggested trying to port the PyPy
runners for our needs. Once we get something up and going we can try to put it
up somewhere for people to make contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many concerns about the benchmarks not being productive and bringing
out too much competition.  My view is that we should try to be as open and
welcoming as the rest of the Python ecosystem.  That is let the numbers speak
for themselves and make these benchmarks something anyone can contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final aspect of the benchmark would be to show off that NumPy is useful for
more then numeric algorithms.  Many people see "Num" and assume there is no use
for their specific needs, but in actuality, NumPy should be thought of as more
a typed array.  This allows fast access to contiguous blocks (although the
element access is often slower than lists).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Going Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is intended to start a wider discussion among the community.  I'm
posting here because there are enough places in the community and I wanted a
single place rather than four or five mailing lists.  The hope is we can start
a repository and get some tests rolling.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="posts"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="NumPy"></category><category term="SciPy"></category></entry></feed>