<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Codematician</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/scipy-tag.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2013-07-07T21:08:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>NumPy SciPy Benchmarks</title><link href="/blog/2013/07/07/numpy-scipy-benchmarks/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-07T21:08:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Andy R. Terrel</name></author><id>tag:,2013-07-07:blog/2013/07/07/numpy-scipy-benchmarks/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At PyCon2013, a group of about 30 developers got together to discuss
NumPy and SciPy.  The room mostly included folks that use NumPy and
SciPy extensively, such as myself, a few who were just learning, and
several core contributors (if not currently in the past), such as Eric
Jones, Travis Oliphant, Anthony Scopatz, and Jake Vanderplas.  It was
an impromptu meeting, as most birds of a feather sessions are, so I
don't think we even got the full number of interested participants at
PyCon2013.  The scientific large support at PyCon was surprising,
since most of us scientists think the wider Python ecosystem leaves us
behind in many of their activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were three topics we discussed: briefly about the development and
maintenance of the libraries, about the use of newer technologies, e.g. Cython,
PyPy, Copperhead, Numba, and finally about having a benchmark for new
implementations of NumPy to see how complete they are.  Since there were not
very many core developers in the room, it was hard to really push a topic on
the development side but the other two topics were the most discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To briefly summarize the maintenance and future plans section, I asked about
how the community was doing since I've been organizing this whole conference
thing and haven't been on the mailing lists in a while. Travis mentioned that
NumFOCUS was trying to raise money for the projects, especially around the
topic of paying a maintainer.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Miniature Applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we turn to the topic of benchmarks.  At the end we decided that there are
at least two types of benchmarks that are really needed by the community.
First, is a set of miniature applications that show off the tools well.  Since
there is such a wide variety of tools available right now, it is difficult to
know what to invest in as a developer.  Ian Osvald mentioned his book that
includes one of the only major comparisons I've seen in the tools.  I suggested
we look at how the Mantevo project implemented its mini-apps for the US DOE.
Another suggestion was to organize the applications in the seven dwarfs
of scientific computing suggested by Phil Collela. I believe these have been
renamed to motifs and extended to eleven by the Berkeley crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea moving forward will be to collect a number of applications, give a
reference implementation, and accept contributions showing how to implement
them in a Python runnable way.  The idea is not to make everyone use Python for
everything but to show off the capabilities of Python as an integration (and
implementation) platform.  One participant brought up that we could have a site
like the Computer Language Benchmarks, while we agreed in spirit enough of us
do not like that benchmark because of its purist ideas that applications should
stick to a single language.  To be friendly to vendor solutions, I'm willing to
accept closed runtimes but since the point is to highlight the code, all code
must be free and open, preferably BSD.  I am sure we will refine the rules as
we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;NumPy Benchmarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matti, a contributor to NumPyPy, brought up the idea of creating a suite of
benchmarks to compare different implementations of NumPy.  The idea here is
once again not to compete ruthlessly for fame and glory, but rather provide a
baseline for developer to hit when implementing alternatives and users to know
how complete and single implementation is. Right now I know of several NumPy
implementations (or close to implementations), e.g., NumPyPy, Numba,
Copperhead, and a benchmark will be a welcome addition to the tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan to start off will be to grab out some tests from the NumPy regression
tests and grab a benchmark runner.  Matti suggested trying to port the PyPy
runners for our needs. Once we get something up and going we can try to put it
up somewhere for people to make contributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many concerns about the benchmarks not being productive and bringing
out too much competition.  My view is that we should try to be as open and
welcoming as the rest of the Python ecosystem.  That is let the numbers speak
for themselves and make these benchmarks something anyone can contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final aspect of the benchmark would be to show off that NumPy is useful for
more then numeric algorithms.  Many people see "Num" and assume there is no use
for their specific needs, but in actuality, NumPy should be thought of as more
a typed array.  This allows fast access to contiguous blocks (although the
element access is often slower than lists).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Going Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is intended to start a wider discussion among the community.  I'm
posting here because there are enough places in the community and I wanted a
single place rather than four or five mailing lists.  The hope is we can start
a repository and get some tests rolling.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category><category term="NumPy"></category><category term="SciPy"></category></entry><entry><title>SciPy2013 Recap</title><link href="/blog/2013/07/05/scipy2013-recap/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-05T12:28:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Andy R. Terrel</name></author><id>tag:,2013-07-05:blog/2013/07/05/scipy2013-recap/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been a week since the end of &lt;a href="http://conference.scipy.com/scipy2013/"&gt;SciPy2013&lt;/a&gt;, where I was co-chair, and I'm just now catching my breath.  It was an amazing event with so many innovative and forward looking trends that I won't be able to give them enough credence, ever.  When I took on the role as co-chair, my guiding goal was to provide a home to scientific researcher engineers, whether they are in government labs, industry, or academia.  Just as &lt;a href="http://pyvideo.org/video/2041/scipy-2013-keynote-the-new-scientific-publishers-1"&gt;William Schroeder said in his keynote&lt;/a&gt;, we are the new scientific publishers and are the driving force behind much of the technology that is changing the world.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Favorite Moments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give a list of the best moments for me at SciPy2013, I'm sure I will be
commenting on them throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SciPy Proceedings have moved to a fully open peer review process for more details see &lt;a href="http://stefanv.github.io/blog/2013/06/27/scipy2013-proceedings/"&gt;Stefan van der Walt's blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a huge number of commits to 18 projects. Including these
highlights (mostly gleaned from &lt;a
href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23scipy2013&amp;src=typd"&gt;#scipy2013&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matplotlib had over a dozen contributors (including a 10K LOC patch
  review).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scikit-Image now runs on Python 3 and 2 from single code base (without
  2to3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IPython developers sequestered themselves to focus on the ever-promised
  1.0 released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contributers to over 16 projects came together to &lt;a
  href="https://github.com/IgnitionProject/ignition/wiki/CodeGenComposability_Scipy2013"&gt;discuss
  commonalities with the compiler technology&lt;/a&gt; that is being reproduced in
  each other's code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know of any other major achievements at SciPy2013 sprints.  We need to collect these stories to help convince sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had &amp;gt;350 people attend, &amp;gt;500 &lt;a href="http://eventifier.co/event/scipy2013/"&gt;people tweeting&lt;/a&gt;, social events almost every night, &lt;a href="http://pyvideo.org/category/37/scipy-2013"&gt;139 videos&lt;/a&gt; including &lt;a href=http://conference.scipy.org/scipy2013/tutorials_schedule.php"&gt;12 amazing tutorials&lt;/a&gt; diving into every aspect of science, and over 6% of the conference either named Matt or from France.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hosted a gathering of Women in Science with a wide array of participants with the help of PyLadies, The Python Software Foundation, and NumFOCUS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over 10 BoFs that provided for a much more participatory discussion on major topics facing our community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet another &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=ywHqIEv3xXg#t=1892s"&gt;completely ridiculous lightning talk from Matt Terry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again I want to give a shout out to all our wonderful sponsors! Without them there would be no SciPy conference (or at least one with less BBQ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other's words&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also a list of other people discussing the conference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://technicaldiscovery.blogspot.com/2013/07/thoughts-after-scipy-2013-and-specific.html"&gt;Travis Oliphant&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://asmeurersympy.wordpress.com/2013/07/02/scipy-2013/"&gt;Aaron Meurer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/blog/2013/04/swc-at-scipy2013.html"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ondrejcertik.blogspot.com/2013/07/my-impressions-from-scipy-2013.html"&gt;Ondrej Certik&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://astrocompute.wordpress.com/2013/07/02/scipy-2013-from-a-distance/"&gt;Bruce Berriman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://hairycode.org/2013/06/25/scipy-2013-day-one/"&gt;Hairy Code&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hairycode.org/2013/06/25/scipy-2013-day-two/"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hairycode.org/2013/06/26/scipy-2013-day-three/"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://hairycode.org/2013/06/28/scipy-2013-day-threefour/"&gt;4/5&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Again please let me know of any other postings and I will add them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category><category term="SciPy"></category></entry><entry><title>Participate at SciPy2013</title><link href="/blog/2013/04/24/participate-at-scipy/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-24T18:41:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Andy R. Terrel</name></author><id>tag:,2013-04-24:blog/2013/04/24/participate-at-scipy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href="https://conference.scipy.org/scipy2013/registration.php"&gt;early registration deadline&lt;/a&gt;
is rapidly approaching for SciPy2013, and all our decisions on speakers are
out.  This year was really tough as we had more submission than ever at a
quality that exceeded all my expectations. If you submitted something and
haven't heard from us, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you missed the deadline for proposals, I want to elaborate on a number of
ways you can still participate.  While the material for the official program is
closed, we have ample opportunities for more spontaneous contributions for all
attendees. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join the community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speak at Lightning talks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hack at the sprints&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participate in BoFs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Join the community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we have a number of opportunities to help get acquainted with
learning how to contribute.  Starting with two days of beginner tutorials to
teach the basic tools of our community and a tutorial on contributing to NumPy,
the core of almost all scientific python projects.  If you are new to the
ecosystem or an old hand needing to know the ends and outs of contribution the
tutorials are there to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have teamed up with the Austin PyLadies to present some material on how and
why to contribute to open source communities. It's well known that open source
communities can be difficult to navigate and folks are not always polite.  We
hope to show some perspectives on contributing and what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lightning Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we don't all have a story of printing NumPy arrays to QR codes and
scanning them to get around bureaucracy, lightning talks remain one of the most
fun parts of the conference.  Tell us about your new venture, your craziest
hack, your nerdiest tech rant, or whatever you feel best fills your five
minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hack at Sprints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sprints start Friday and we hope to have a large number of the core
projects all come out.  In the next week we should have sign ups on the
website. Sprints are not only a good time to focus on your project for a few
days, it also is a place where the experts in the scientific python will be in
the room.  Any quick bugs or small details to ask can have a much quicker
iteration cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we are also encouraging folks to not wait until Friday to start
hacking, and I know some of you wouldn't wait anyways.  I'm looking at you
Fernando, Jake, Wes,  ....  But this year we will have about 6 break out rooms
just right for 4 to 8 people to brainstorm and hack in between things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Birds of Feathers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we have nine time spaces open for Birds of a Feather sessions.  I
personally find these session the best to discuss ideas with the conference
attendees. We will have a sign up on the web soon as well.  Some ideas I
have floated include: state of the project BoFs discuss the future of many
projects, evolution of the publication in the state of open code and data, and
best ways for teaching scientist python.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category><category term="SciPy"></category></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on the SciPy Conference</title><link href="/blog/2012/10/08/thoughts-on-the-scipy-conference/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-08T01:24:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Andy R. Terrel</name></author><id>tag:,2012-10-08:blog/2012/10/08/thoughts-on-the-scipy-conference/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For SciPy2012 I was given the privilege of serving as the co-chair of the
program committee.  The experience was exciting and rewarding as I was able to
affect what I view as one of the most important conferences for the scientific
world. Now, that's a pretty bold statement and I'm not going to dwell on it
long here, but essentially many conferences people go to show off;
SciPy is a conference where people come to learn best practices.  And when young
scientists are able to see science rock stars like Joshua Bloom lift up the
covers and show off how his scientific process works, it changes their entire
workflow creating more efficient, better scientists. With that said, I would
like to focus more on my opinions about the state of the conference, its
successes and failures, and how I believe the conference should be transformed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The state of the SciPy Community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a bit strange being the co-chair of the program committee at SciPy2012,
because prior to 2012 I had only attended one SciPy conference.  Of course, I
have known about the conference for years and have tried to go many times but
life has always gotten in the way.  Additionally, I came to the scientific
Python community after most everything had evolved to a pretty high level of
quality.  Sure there are bits and pieces that could use some polish, but
largely I feel that my contributions have all been cosmetic (although the GSOC
students I have mentored have done phenomenal work). This puts me at a bit of a
disadvantage to extol any long history of the SciPy community, but I'm sure
someone will let me know where I get things right and wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some interesting divides in the community.  For example, SciPy can
refer to many different things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The US SciPy conference,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The international SciPy conference series,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Python package named scipy,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The basic scientific computing stack used by most pythonistas, and/or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any piece of code slightly related to science and Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this article, when I say SciPy I am talking about the US SciPy conference
(since if I usually can't afford to make it to SciPy in Austin, TX, I sure
can't afford to go to Brussels or India) and a mix of the other topics.  SciPy
was originally a set of friends who got together in a room at Caltech to chat
and hack about the scipy package.  They use to have these talks from the core
devs where each gave a summary of the package and largely discuss technical
issues around these packages.  As of late, the conference has turned into much
more of a place where any scientist or technical computing professional can go
and hear about a very wide variety of topics on science and Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This change in community is both a good and a bad thing.  It means that at
coffee, there are a lot of strange faces and let's be honest if we were the
most social crowd we wouldn't have spent a non-trivial amount of our lives
pouring over code and mathematics.  Second we seem to have lost some of the
core devs attention.  For example, in the months preceding the conference the
numpy mailing list had turned into a pretty nasty flamewar.  At the conference,
I only saw one of the major contributors to the numpy code base.  I find the
fact that SciPy isn't the most important event on the calendar for these devs
kind of surprising.  After all this is where you core devs are the gurus
everyone has come to be inspired by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that we are able to see a more accurate view of the
penetration of Python in science.  But not only science, pretty much all
technical computing areas of industry, academia, and government were
represented.  The conference had a record number of attendees and submissions,
in fact this was the first SciPy that we knew of where people received
rejections.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Successes and Failures of SciPy 2012&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways SciPy is a great conference, but in other ways it is lacking.  I
want to explore a few of these ideas, get feedback from the community, and put
the consensus into action.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Success&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it ain't broke don't fix it ~ Anonymous&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Topics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past two years, there have been two special topics.  Last year was Big Data
and Core Issues; this year we did High Performance Computing and Visualization.
The truth was that we picked these topics because a few motivated folks were
excited about them.  This is true about the domain session this year as well.
Lauren and I chatted, I gave names and she went calling people down to get the
right set of talks.  Largely I think this works, but I don't like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't like it because the community wasn't really involved and when you have
a couple of people picking the overall direction of a community, it largely
becomes a clique.  If we want to keep a vibrant community, I think these topics
are really important as they are aimed at bringing in people from outside our
community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, my proposal this year would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine Learning, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geographic Information Systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both topics that came out during the surveys and are a broad cutting
technologies.  Machine Learning should be a no-brainer as the Big Data world
needs it more than ever, but GIS is a bit harder for me to predict being a
break out success.  Of course last year I thought HPC would be the small topic
and Vis a bigger draw, but I was dead wrong.  We could of had the whole
conference on PyHPC (if you want sort of thing, check out the SuperComputing
Conference pyHPC workshop).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fabulous plenaries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I believe the plenaries were really off the chart.  I was actually
recruited to help out after the plenaries had already been chosen, so this was
really Stéfan and Warren's doing.  I really like the format as well. A talk
about a well-known package, a science talk about the things people are able to
accomplish with the tools, and a look into industry and how our community
relates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have quite a few ideas about how to replicate this formula, but I believe we
should probably have some discussion from the community.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Poster session&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poster session was great.  There was a lot of interaction between people at
the session.  I'm somewhat beside myself on the session though.  I thought it
would be better during the reception, but we couldn't get the posters in the
reception room and be visible during the entire conference.  I really liked
the poster session and hope to see it in the future.  One fact of science
conferences is that usually it is harder to get funding if you don't have
something to present.  Posters are a great way to increase participation,
although I do wonder if we need to go to three parallel tracks in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Domain science symposiums&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The symposiums at the end of the day were much sparser than the day.  This was
expected, but they play an important role.  As the main session includes a
large number of folks that have quite different domains, these sessions allowed
for topic specifics to be discussed.  More and more domain conferences are
including sessions on Python, but SciPy allows for sessions to grab the
attention of Python experts who are often able to give fresh advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Develop success from failures. Discouragement and failure are two of the
surest stepping stones to success.  ~ Dale Carnegie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure is probably too harsh a word for what I discuss in this section.  It's
more adequately, "Things that disappointed Andy."  And as most people who know
me know, I'm not afraid to tell you why I'm disappointed (only I usually use
harsher words).  At any rate, I believe in &lt;a href="http://www.admittingfailure.com/"&gt;admitting
failure&lt;/a&gt; and want to discuss a few things I
would like to rectify.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Community involvement&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, the conference is put on by about four people.  Sure there is
a longer list on the website, but the brunt of the work falls on a few.  I
would like to see this change.  For example, look at how PyCon is run.  There
are more volunteers than you can count. While Enthought is an amazing
institutional sponsor of the event, they only have a small number of resources
to put into the event.  My impression is that these resources are over
exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is time we as a community come together to setup structures for more
community participation.  For example, the websites need work, the process of
reviewing papers needs work, there needs to be more logistical help at the
meeting, and so on.  My guess is that most people don't even know that they
could be helping. To even start though we need to build a volunteer network and
appropriate web presence to give volunteers things to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Diversity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matt Davis brought this up on Twitter, but I want to echo it louder.  There was
a discouraging lack of diversity at SciPy.  I believe there were 100 males to
every female and very few minorities.  When talking to a few people about this,
the general view was that there just aren't women coders around.  I think this is
really wrong, I think that women coders either don't know about SciPy or don't
care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings up how do you attract female coders?  One metric given to me is
that conferences with women plenary speakers and/or women on the executive
staff have 50% more women participants.  I look at the places we advertised and
we didn't focus on any female or minority organizations.  Closing this gap will
only make our community more vibrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Industry/Academia interactions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SciPy is a place where there are a few industrial partners but there could be
many more. The problem I saw on the program committee was that anyone who
submitted work on closed source software were negatively impacted.  We are an
open source community but hundreds (thousands?) of companies use our tools.
Industrial partners that come back to the community and talk about how to
interact more can only be a good thing.  For one it will give us a since of the
impact that SciPy has beyond the halls of academia.  It will heighten our
profile among young developers as they are able to come to SciPy to meet
potential employers.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suggestion here would be to have vendor booths and a recruitment event.  I
would even go as far to suggest hosting a few sponsor speaking sessions.  Open
source is often supported by industry, just as the scipy stack has been
supported by Enthought for years.  Inviting industry to our meeting will make it
more visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Social Media&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of social media at the conference is quite surprising.  Are we all old
fuddies who don't know how to use social media to discuss?  It is quite
exciting to go to a conference where the social media around the conference is
working well.  It allows for more dialog among the participants and thus a
greater shared experience.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, I would like to see a greater use of Twitter, G+ and Facebook
throughout the event, including planning. Connecting our community may even
heal all those fights we have on mailing lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lack of Core Developers&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've already touched on this, but one last failure is the lack of core project
developers at the conference.  Sure people have lots competing with their time,
but this is the conference dedicated to the code we spend so much free time
on.  Conversations at SciPy are still having an effect on the directions of
codes (in fact today scipy.users had a long conversation about the scipy domain which
was hotly discussed at the sprints).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The few ideas I have on bringing the coders back include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More sprinting (space every night &lt;em&gt;all night&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sessions dedicated to core projects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More organization around BoFs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conference sponsorship for devs to attend conference &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Vision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay 2000 words in and I'm sure you are getting bored.  But I've said this
before and I'll say it again.  There is no reason SciPy shouldn't be as large
as PyCon.  While there are certainly more users of the Python language, our
community is always one of the featured groups when Python users are
discussed.  The suggestions I outlined above are only a small set of comments I
really have, but they are the ones I feel probably need a broader discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me the vision of SciPy should be simple.  SciPy is the fuel of the
scientific Python movement.  It is where producers and consumers of
scientific and technical code come to learn from each other and make each other
better scientists and coders.  SciPy as a conference should be inclusive of all
technical disciplines and help mentor novice programmers. Finally, it should be
the place where we inject new life into our projects, hack the wild ideas we
only dream about, and submit pull requests that change the face of science.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Python"></category><category term="SciPy"></category></entry></feed>